翻译: J.T.F Kayvan 三好
电波字幕组 诚心诚译
校对: 三好 Nikki
后期: 英俊君
压制: 英俊君
醉 乡 民 谣
煤灯咖啡馆 1961
*绞死我吧 绞死我吧*
*Hang me, oh, hang me*
*我已行将死去*
*I'll be dead and gone*
*绞死我吧 绞死我吧*
*Hang me, oh, hang me*
*我已行将死去*
*I'll be dead and gone*
*我不在乎被绞死*
*I wouldn't mind the hanging*
*只是可怜见的 我不想永远困在一方坟墓*
*But the laying in the grave so long Poor boy*
*我也曾游走四方*
*I've been all around this world*
开普吉拉多 密苏里州的一个地方
*足迹遍布开普吉拉多*
*Been all around Cape Girardeau*
*以及阿肯色州的一些地方*
*Parts of Arkansas*
*足迹遍布开普吉拉多*
*All around Cape Girardeau*
*以及阿肯色州的一些地方*
*Parts of Arkansas*
*我真他妈的饿极了*
*I got so goddamn hungry*
*可怜见的 一棵稻草就能将我遮挡*
*I could hide behind a straw Poor boy*
*我游遍万水千山*
*I've been all around this world*
*爬上高山*
*Went up on the mountain*
*那是我坚定了立场的地方*
*There I made my stand
*爬上高山*
*Went up on the mountain*
*那是我坚定了立场的地方*
*There I made my stand*
*扛一把来福在肩头*
*A rifle on my shoulder*
*还有一把匕首在手 可怜的孩子啊*
*And a dagger in my hand Poor boy*
*我已踏遍五湖四海*
*I been all around this world*
*用一捆绳子勒紧我的脖子*
*Put the rope around my neck*
*把我吊的老高*
*Hang me up so high*
*用一捆绳子勒紧我的脖子*
*Put the rope around my neck*
*他们把我吊的老高*
*They hung me up so high*
*我临死前听到的最后一句*
*The last words I heard 'em say:*
*可怜的孩子啊 一下就好*
*"Won't be long now 'fore you die Poor boy"*
*我已周游完这个世界*
*I've been all around this world*
*绞死我吧 绞死我吧*
*So hang me, oh, hang me*
*我已行将死去*
*And I'll be dead and gone*
*绞死我吧 绞死我吧*
*Hang me, oh, hang me*
*我将与世长辞*
*And I'll be dead and gone*
*绞死我又能怎样*
*Wouldn't mind the hanging*
*只是可怜见的 我不想永远困在一方坟墓*
*But the laying in the grave so long Poor boy*
*我也曾游走四方*
*I've been all around this world*
你们之前可能听过这首
You probably heard that one before.
如果一首歌从来不曾新过 也永远不会过时 估计就是民谣了
If it was never new and it never gets old, then it's a folk song.
- 你和Mikey一起唱过这首歌  -是的
- You and Mikey used to do that song.  - Yeah.
孩子 你昨天晚上真是一团糟啊
Boy, you were some mess last night.
是 对不起 Pappi 我是个傻逼
Yeah, sorry, Pappi. I'm an asshole.
我才不在乎 音乐而已
I don't give a shit. It's just music.
你一个朋友在后巷
Your friend is out back.
我的朋友
My friend?
他说是你的朋友 一个西装男
Said he was a friend of yours. Guy in a suit.
你这货挺有趣 哈
You a funny boy, huh?
什么
What?
管不住你的大嘴 哈 可笑的东西
Had to open your big mouth, huh, funny boy?
管不住 什么
I had to... What?
只是为了糊口 你 你是谁
That's what I do for a living. Who...? Who are you?
糊口
What you do.
不好意思 我 我做了什
I'm sorry, what...? What did I...?
你昨天在观众席上大放厥词
You sit there in the audience last night, yelling your crap.
有没有搞错 那是演出啊 怎么可能不张嘴
Oh, for christssake. You yell stuff, man. It's a show.
那不是你的演出
It wasn't your show.
又不是戏剧 混球 不就是他妈的酒吧演出 嗷
It's not the opera, jackass. It's a fucking basket hou... Unh!
我们马上就要离开这臭粪坑了 你在里面享受吧
We're leaving this fucking cesspool. You can have it.
糊口
What you do.
有人吗
Hello?
谢谢让我睡沙发 抱歉昨天晚上打扰了
不 不行
No, no...
妈的
Shit.
该死的
Goddamn it.
有人在么
Hello?
你好
Hi.
你能
Could you, um...?
你能帮我照看一下这猫吗
Could I leave this cat with you?
- 我  - 是的
- With me?  - Yeah, it's, um...
它是Gorfeins夫妇的猫 只要等到他们夫妻俩有一个回来就行了
It's the Gorfeins' cat. Just till one of them gets back?
我吗
With me?
它溜出来的 我又没钥匙
It slipped out and I don't have the key.
帮忙照看一下吧 到他们回来就好
Could you just keep it till they get back?
我得管电梯
I have to run the elevator.
这又不麻烦对吧 它是Gorfeins夫妇的猫
I mean, that's not a problem, is it? It's the Gorfeins' cat.
我得管电梯啊
I have to run the elevator.
- 社会学系  - 我找Gorfein教授
- Sociology.  - Professor Gorfein, please.
他在上课
He's in a lecture now.
- 要留言吗  - 呃
- Could I take a message?  - Uh...
好的 麻烦你转告他
Yeah, could you...? Could you just tell him:
"别担心 猫在Llewyn这儿"
"Don't worry, Llewyn has the cat"?
"猫叫Llewyn"
"Llewyn is the cat."
不是 猫"在"Llewyn 我是Llewyn 猫在我这儿
No, Llewyn "Has" The cat. I'm Llewyn. I have his cat.
草
Oh, shit.
- 嘿 Nunzio  - 嘿 他们不在家
- Hey, Nunzio.  - Yeah. They ain't home, though.
我知道  我能借用你家的防火梯吗
Yeah, I know. Can I use your fire escape?
嗨
Hi.
- 最近怎么样  - 很好
- How we doing?  - We're doing great.
真的吗
Really?
新专辑卖的不错吗
The new record's doing well?
呃 "咱们"怎么样 老实说 不是很好
Uh, how "We" Doing. Not so hot, I gotta be honest.
- Ginny <辛辛那提>在哪儿  - 什么
- Ginny, where's Cincinnati?  - What?
- <辛辛那提> 它不在这儿  - 应该在的啊
- Cincinnati, it's not in here.  - It should be in there.
都说了不在
It's not in here, I'm telling you.
- 那是  - <辛辛那提>
- Is it...?  - Cincinnati?
- 对  - 我找到了
- Yeah.  - I got it.
什么
What?
- 我找到了  - 你找到了
- I got it.  - You got Cincinnati?
是的 你要么
Yeah, you want it?
- 能给我么  - 要我拿进去么
- Could I have it?  - Should I bring it in?
- 好  - 你是不是欠我点什么
- Yeah.  - Do you owe me something?
你肯定欠了我什么
You have to owe me something.
我倒是想
I wish.
人们需要时间
People need time, you know.
得去了解你 认可你的单人演奏
Get to know you, buy you as a solo act.
即使他们知道你单飞了
Even know you're a solo act.
- <辛辛那提>也不算佳作  - 就是那个 对吧
- Cincinnati is not good.  - That's it, right?
是的 就是这个 老天开开眼吧
Yeah, this is it, God help me.
我们是二人组时也没人知道我们
Nobody knew us when we were a duo.
你说的好像Mike和我之前多出名一样
It's not like me and Mike were ever a big act.
又不需要向重新
It's not a big reeducation
向大众推出我
for the public.
Mel
Mel?
Mel.
最近怎么样 小子
How you doing, kid?
Mel 就算你不给我新专辑的预付款
Mel, there was no advance on my solo record.
也总该有些版权费吧
There's gotta be some royalty.
该死的 天气开始冷起来了
Fucking christssake, it's cold out.
我都没件冬大衣
I don't even have a winter coat.
天呐 你开玩笑吧
Jesus Christ. You're kidding me.
- 拿着吧孩子  - Mel 不可以
- Take this, kid.  - Mel, no.
我坚持你收下
I insist. I insist.
你不要你该死的大衣 我穿了你穿啥
I don't want your fucking coat. What'll you wear?
- 孩子 我总有办法的  - 这丫的根本就不合身 这
- Kid, I'll get by.  - It won't even fit me. This is...
这就是垃圾 Mel
It's bullshit, Mel.
你别假惺惺了
It's just a big fat fucking bluff.
假惺惺
Bluff?
孩子 你说什么 假惺惺 我给你这个
Kid, what are you ta...? Bluff? I offer you this?
给我滚出去
Get the fuck out of my office.
- 好吧 谢谢你的外套  - 什么
- All right, thanks for the coat.  - What?
好吧 等一下
All right, well, wait.
妈的
Aw, shit.
我给你四十吧
Let me give you 40 bucks.
- 这猫怎么回事  - 呃 不好意思
- Explain the cat.  - Yeah, sorry.
它是Gorfeins的猫
It's, uh... It's the Gorfeins' cat.
- 我昨晚在那儿过夜  - 它叫什么
- I crashed there last night.  - What's its name?
呃 我不知道 他偷溜出来的
Uh, I don't know. He snuck out the door when...
你以为你今晚能待这儿吗
Do you think you're staying here tonight?
你以为...呃
"Do you think...?" Um...
- 我想来着 Jim在吗  - Jim不在
- I was hoping to. Is Jim around?  - Jim's not here.
我们让Troy待这儿
We told Troy he could crash here.
Troy Nelson 你好
Troy Nelson. How are you?
- 你好 我是Llewyn Davis  - 哦
- How you doing? Llewyn Davis.  - Oh.
你好 我听过你的音乐
Hello. I've heard your music,
还有不少你的好话
and heard many nice things
从Jim和Jean还有其他人那儿听说的
about you from Jim and Jean and from others.
哈哈哈 你绝不可能从Jean那儿听到我任何的好话
Ha-ha-ha. You have not heard one nice thing about me from Jean,
绝不 对吧 Troy
ever, have you, Troy?
你告诉Gorferins你会照顾他们的猫
You tell the Gorfeins you'll take care of their cat,
但你却把他带来让我们照看
then bring him here for us to take care of.
我听过Jim和Jean还有其他人讲的好话
I've heard nice things from Jim and Jean and others.
我不是 事情就这么发生了
I didn't... It just happened.
这是只安静的小猫咪 一脸知足样
It's a peaceful cat. It's very contented.
我今晚不能待在这儿了吗
So I can't stay here tonight?
听着 我们让Troy待这儿了
Look, we told Troy he could stay.
我们不会因为你可能出现就一直空着沙发
We don't keep the couch free on the chance you'll show up.
如果不方便的话
If this is awkward,
今晚表演完后我可以搭车回迪克斯堡
I could hitch back to Fort Dix after I perform tonight.
别说傻话 我们已经答应让你睡沙发了
Don't be silly. We offered you the couch.
你在哪儿表演
You're gigging somewhere?
Troy要在"煤灯"表演 我们在那儿和Jim碰面
Troy is playing at the Gaslight. We're meeting Jim there.
那好吧  我可以睡地板的
Well, I could sleep on the floor here,
Llewyn可以睡沙发
and Llewyn could have the couch.
我不是个瞎讲究的人
I'm certainly not a man of comforts.
或者 我也可以表演完后搭车回迪克斯堡
Alternately, I could hitch back to Fort Dix after the show.
Llewyn和他的猫睡地板
Llewyn can sleep on the floor with his cat.
它是Gorfeins的猫
It's the Gorfeins' cat.
我怀孕了
搞毛啊
What the fuck?
*教训来的太晚*
*It's a lesson too late For the learner*
*脆弱不堪 脆弱不堪*
*Made of sand, made of sand*
*眨眼之间 我的灵魂已经*
*In the wink of an eye My soul is turning*
*交到你手上 交到你手上*
*In your hand, in your hand*
*你要不辞而别了吗*
*Are you going away With no word of farewell?*
*不留下一丝踪迹可循吗*
*Will there be not a trace left behind?*
*好吧 我应该更加爱你的*
*Well, I could've loved you better*
- Llewyn  - 嘿
- Llewyn.  - Hey.
- 很高兴见到你  - 嘿
- Good to see you.  - Hey.
*我不是故意这么残忍*
*I didn't mean to be unkind*
*你要知道那是我最不想的事情*
*You know that was The last thing on my mind*
*你有一堆的理由离去*
*You've got reasons aplenty For going*
- 你觉得怎么样  - 什么
- What do you think?  - What?
他 Troy
Him, Troy.
很好的艺人
Wonderful performer.
- 是吗  - 很出色
- Is he?  - Wonderful.
*求你别走*
*Please don't go*
- 他能做的更好点吗  - 嘘
- Does he have a higher function?  - Shh!
*你要离开*
*Are you going away*
我要买点喝的
I need a drink.
*不留下一句再见*
*With no word of farewell?*
*没有改变*
*Will there be not a change*
听着 Jim 我本来不想提这件事的
Look, Jim, I didn't wanna mention this
当着Jean的面 你知道她的反应
in front of Jean. You know how she gets.
- 什么意思  - 就是
- What do you mean?  - Just, uh, you know...
我想 我想借点钱
I need to... I need to borrow some money.
我很快就可以还给你的 和上次的一起还
I can pay you back really soon, that and the last loan.
我认识了个姑娘 搞出了点意外需要解决
There's a girl I know who's in trouble and needs to get fixed.
- 又来  - 不是同一个
- Not again.  - This is a different girl.
别告诉Jean
Don't tell Jean.
不告诉Jean我就拿不到钱
I can't get the money without Jean knowing.
- 没事 我们可以  - 不 不 不 没关系
- It's okay. We can...  - No, no, no, it's okay, it's okay.
我去其它地方借好了
I'll find it somewhere else.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
谢谢
Thank you.
今晚观众中有位很特别的朋友
There's someone special in the audience tonight
他们会起来帮我
who'll maybe get up and help me out here
- 只要你们大声鼓掌  - 我没带吉他
- if you give a round of applause.  - I don't have my guitar.
我知道你们知道并喜欢他们
I know that you folks know them and love them.
女士们先生们 有请Jim和Jean
Ladies and gentlemen, Jim and Jean.
哦
Oh.
*如果你错过了我乘的火车*
*If you miss the train I'm on*
*你就知道我已经走了*
*You will know that I am gone*
*你会听到鸣笛声隐隐响起*
*You can hear the whistle blow*
*在那百里之外*
*A hundred miles*
*百里之外 百里之外*
*A hundred miles, a hundred miles*
*你会听到那鸣笛声隐隐响起*
*You can hear the whistle blow*
*在那百里之外*
*A hundred miles*
*主啊 一百 两百*
*Lord, I'm one, Lord, I'm two*
*三百 四百*
*Lord, I'm three, Lord, I'm four*
*主啊 我已经离家五百里*
*Lord, I'm 500 miles*
*那么远 那么远*
*Away from home*
*离家那么远 离家那么远*
*Away from home, away from home*
*主啊 我已经离家五百里*
*Lord, I'm 500 miles*
*那么远 那么远*
*Away from home*
*衣不蔽体*
*Not a shirt on my back*
*身无分文*
*Not a penny to my name*
*主啊 我不能这样回家*
*Lord, I can't go back home This a-way*
怎么
What?
*这样回家 这样回家*
*This a-way, this a-way*
*主啊 我不能*
*Lord, I can't go back home*
*这样回家*
*This a-way*
*如果你错过了我乘坐的火车*
*If you miss the train I'm on*
*你会知道我已离去*
*You will know that I am gone*
小子 他们还不错嘛
Boy, they're not bad.
*你会听到鸣笛声隐隐响起*
*You can hear the whistle blow*
嗯哼
Uh-huh.
那个Jean
That Jean,
*在那百里之外*
*A hundred miles*
我想上她
I'd like to fuck her.
*百里之外 百里之外*
*A hundred miles, a hundred miles*
*你会听到鸣笛声隐隐响起*
*You can hear the whistle blow*
*在那百里之外*
*A hundred miles*
嗯
Mm.
抱歉
Sorry.
天还早 不想吵醒你们的
It's early. I tried not to wake anyone.
唔
Mm-hm.
味道真好
Well, that was very good.
接下来是什么
What's next?
什么意思
What do you mean?
你要投奔哪里吗
Do you plug yourself in somewhere?
没
No.
好吧
Well,
该报道了
report for duty.
我要回迪克斯堡
Back to Fort Dix.
他们要把你变成杀人机器吗
They making you a killing machine?
没 估计和你想的不一样
No, it's probably different from what you imagine.
训练确实比较严苛 可能你指的是那个
There's the discipline, which is what you're referring to.
但是我以那些为乐
I thrive on that.
只是武装也是工作的一部分
Weaponry is part of the job.
但那不是我的菜 我都不赞成战争
Armaments are not my thing. I don't even approve of war toys.
- 算是你的职业么  - 不 不算 我几个月后就退役了
- Is it a career?  - No, no. I get out in a few months.
Bud Grossman有意签下我
Bud Grossman has expressed interest in representing me.
Bud Grossman 60年代美国民谣复兴时他签下了包括鲍勃迪伦在内众多民谣巨星
Bud Grossman
Bud Grossman?
他人怎么样
What's he like?
Grossman先生是个好人 一直很支持我
Mr. Grossman is a wonderful man. He's been very supportive.
我上次休假就去了他在芝加哥的俱乐部演奏
I played at his club in Chicago on my last furlough,
那时候我刚从德国回来
right after I got back from Germany.
你见过Elvis吗
Did you meet Elvis?
没有 怎么每个人都这么问
No. Everyone asks that.
没有 我没见到猫王
No, I did not meet Private Presley.
那么说你在应验之梦表演过
So you played at the Gate of Horn.
是的
Yes.
我猜Grossman先生喜欢我的表演
Mr. Grossman liked what he saw, I guess.
他认为我可以以此为生
He thinks I can have a career.
哼嗯
Hm.
替我谢谢Jim和Jean
Thank Jim and Jean for me.
嗯
Mm-hm.
再会
So long.
你叫什么来着
What's your name again?
操 糟了
Oh, shit.
不 不
No. No.
操 妈的 靠
Fuck. Goddamn it. Oh, shit.
草
Fuck.
该死的 猫
Shit. Cat.
靠 小猫咪
Fuck. Kitty?
靠 靠
Fuck. Fuck.
多谢你保持安静 混球
Thanks for keeping quiet, asshole.
我冷死了 我们能聊聊吗
I'm freezing. Can we talk?
这里不行 滚
Not here. Fuck you.
抱歉 你是哪个意思 滚 还是 操你
I'm sorry, which? "Out" Or "Fuck you"?
我们出去走走吧 能借我Jim的外套吗
Let's go out. Can I borrow Jim's coat?
我不知道
I don't know.
- 你不知道是不是我的  - 我怎么知道
- You don't know if it's mine?  - No. How would I know?
- 所以还是有可能是Jim的  - 是的 你个混球
- So it could be Jim's.  - Yes, asshole.
等一下 说明白点 不管谁的你都不想要 是吧
Wait, you don't want it either way? To be clear.
我给你说明白 混蛋 你个挨千刀的混蛋
To be clear, asshole, you fucking asshole,
如果是Jim的 我就很想要 这就是我要的
I want very much to have it if it's Jim's. That's what I want.
但是既然我不知道 你就不仅把事情搞砸了
But since I don't know, you not only fucked things up
因为你上了我还把我弄怀孕了
by fucking me and maybe making me pregnant,
导致就算孩子不是你的 我也不可能知道
but even if it's not yours, I can't know that.
所以我不得不流掉
So I have to get rid of what
一个可能十分健康的宝宝  我一直想要的宝宝
might be a perfectly fine baby, a baby I want,
什么事儿沾上你就要倒霉
because everything you touch turns to shit.
你就像迈达斯国王的蠢弟弟
Like King Midas's idiot brother.
好吧
Well, okay.
我明白了
I see.
你有认识的医生对吧
You know a doctor, right?
是的
Yes.
从什么时候开始的
From when?
无所谓了 Diane
Whatever, Diane?
是的
Yes.
- 你会付钱是吧  - 是的
- And you'll pay for it?  - Yes.
别告诉Jim 这不用我交代了吧
Don't tell Jim, obviously.
我应该让你戴俩套的
I should've had you wear double condoms.
不对 是我们就不应该上床
Well, we shouldn't have done it
从一开始就不 但是如果你再这么做
in the first place, but if you ever do it again,
再四处留情 虽然不应该
which as a favor to women everywhere, you should not,
但如果你要做 你记得多带个套
but if you do, you should be wearing condom on condom,
然后再缠上绝缘胶带
and then wrap it in electrical tape.
你出门就该把你自己裹在一个巨型套套里
You should just walk around always inside a great big condom
- 因为你就是个人渣  - 好呐
- because you are shit.  - Okay.
作为个人渣 你就不该和任何有生命的物体接触
You should not be in contact with any living thing, being shit.
你也应该听说过 一个巴掌拍不响吧
Have you ever heard the expression, "It takes two to tango"?
去你妈的
Fuck you.
我觉得我们应该
Well, I could say we
等你气消了再讨论
should talk about this when you're less angry,
但那就要等到...
but that would be...
那就要等到
That would be...
- 那要等到什么时候  - 去你妈的
- When would that be?  - Fuck you.
我想Mike了
I miss Mike.
我能求你帮个忙吗
Can I ask you for a favor?
你妈的开玩笑吧
You're joking.
不是为了我 是为了Gorfeins夫妇
It's not for me, it's for the Gorfeins.
他们的猫出走了 你能把你防火梯的窗户开着吗
Their cat got out. Could you leave the fire-escape window open?
现在是大冬天
It's winter.
够那只猫溜进来就行了
Just enough for the cat to squeeze back in?
它会回来的
It could come back.
回我们公寓吗 它在那儿才待了六个小时
To our apartment? It was there, like, six hours.
它为什么会回来
Why would it come back there?
我不知道 我他妈的又不是猫
I don't know, I'm not a fucking cat.
想想吧 我他妈的弄丢了他们的猫 我很内疚
Think about it. I lost their fucking cat. I feel bad about it.
你只为了那个内疚吗
That's what you feel bad about?
你好
Hello.
你的外套呢
Where's your coat?
- 没那么冷  - 你疯了吧
- It's not that cold.  - You out of your mind?
你的音乐怎么样了
So how's the music going?
呃 很好 很好
Uh, pretty good. Pretty good.
很好 这么说你就不需要借钱了
Oh, good. So you don't need to borrow money.
- 事实上 我在想  - 嗯哼
- Actually, I was wondering...  - Uh-huh.
它卖了吗
Is it sold?
- 房子  - 嗯
- The house?  - Yeah.
算是吧
Yeah. Uh-huh.
- 现在在第三方保管呢  - 卖了多少
- I mean, it's in escrow.  - How much?
一万一千五 怎么了
Eleven-five. But why?
- 那可不是我们的房子  - 不是我们的
- It's not our house. - Not our house?
废话 那是爸妈的
Well, yeah. It's Mom and Dad's house.
卖房的钱是他们的赡养费 我们一个子儿都得不到
Llewyn, it goes to his upkeep. We don't get any.
还好你的音乐卖的还行
Good thing your music's going good.
- 抱歉  - 是啊 去他妈的
- I'm sorry.  - Yeah, well, what the fuck?
- Llewyn  - 干吗
- Llewyn.  - What?
- 注意你的措辞  - 哦 不好意思
- The language.  - Oh, yeah, I'm sorry.
我不是你格林尼治村的朋友
I am not one of your Greenwich Village friends.
好的 好
Okay, yeah, yeah.
- 你的海员证书还在吧  - 在啊 怎么了
- You still got your seaman's papers?  - Yeah, why?
- 如果你的音乐路走不  - 干什么 让我退出吗
- Well, if the music's not...  - What? Quit?
在去商船上做事吗
Merchant Marine again?
就活着
Just exist?
哈 活着
Heh, exist?
难道除了你们搞表演的别人都只能算活着吗
Is that what we do outside of show business?
其实没那么差哦 活着
It's not so bad, existing.
- 像老爸吗  - Llewyn
- Like Dad?  - Llewyn.
- 干嘛  - 你怎么能这么说自己的父亲
- What?  - You say that about your own father?
- 什么  - 他就那样苟活着
- What? - That he exists?
我不是那个意思 是你说的
I didn't say... You said it.
- 算了  - 就那么苟活着 就那样是吗
- Forget it.  - That he exists? Like that?
是 我错了
Yeah, yeah, I'm sorry.
- 最近见过他吗  - 见过
- Seen him?  - Yeah.
什么
What?
- 我应该去吗  - 你说呢 他是你爸
- Should I?  - You tell me, he's your father.
呵呵 他当然是
Yeah, he sure is.
哦 我 等一下 你有空吗
Oh, I got... Wait, I got... You got a minute?
我得回去排练
Well, they want me back for rehearsals.
沙利文秀
Sullivan Show.
我有好多粉丝等着我签名
I've got autographs to sign.
- 还有香槟招待会  - 别走
- Champagne reception.  - Don't go away.
我把房子整理了一遍
I cleaned it out, the house.
这里有些东西 我把你的东西都放这箱子里了
There's some stuff. I put your stuff in a box.
那些我觉得你还想要的东西
What I thought you might want.
我不知道 Joy
I don't know, Joy.
直接丢大街上好了
Just stick it out at the curb.
你开玩笑吧 看看这些
Llewyn, are you kidding? Look at this.
你知道这是什么吗
You know what this is?
这是你为了爸妈录的"鲱鱼群"
This is when you recorded "Shoals of Herring" For Morn and Dad.
你 好像是8岁左右吧 超级可爱的
You... Whatever, you're like 8 years old. It's so cute.
你要知道 Joy 在演艺圈
Well, see, Joy, in the entertainment business,
你不能把你练习的那些垃圾流出
you're not supposed to let your practice shit out.
会毁了我的神秘感的
It ruins the mystique.
抱歉 我又不知道演艺圈还有这规定
I'm sorry. I don't know a lot about the entertainment business.
好吧
Yeah, well...
别抱歉了
Don't be sorry.
不 不 不 我会把猫带回去 它挺好的 只是我 呃
No, no, no, I'll bring the cat up. It's fine. I just, uh...
不行 我今天没法带她回去
I can't today, as it turns out. I can't bring her today.
- 他  - 对 他
- Him.  - Him, him, yeah.
- 我可以去接他  - 他在Jim和Jean家玩呢
- But I can get down there. - He's hanging out at Jim and Jean's.
他喜欢他们家
He's... He likes it there.
他好着呢 相信我哦 好着呢
He's fine. Believe me, he's fine.
好吧 但是我去更方便...
Okay. But it's easy for me...
- 不 不 不 他们不在家  - 好吧
- No, no, no. They're not home.  - Okay.
- 他们基本上不着家  - 好吧
- They're never home.  -  All right.
不管怎么样 我不怎么好意思让你
Uh, so... Anyway, I couldn't ask you to do that.
过到村子这边来 Mitch
All the way down to the Village, Mitch.
不 我明天会带她回去的
No, I'll bring her up tomorrow.
- 他 带他回去  - 好的 好的
- Him. Him up tomorrow.  - Right. Okay, good.
记得打电话给Jim 他说有急事
And remember to call Jim. He said it was urgent.
是吗 真有急事吗 我会打给他的 谢了
Yeah, I doubt if it's urgent, but I'll call him. Thanks.
不 他说真有急事
No, no, he said it's urgent.
今天下午哥伦比亚公司有个录音
It's a session this afternoon at Columbia.
有人生病退出了
Somebody got sick and dropped out.
他觉得你会喜欢
He thought you'd like the work.
什么 什么
What? What?
他有要我带吉他吗
Did he say that I need my guitar?
应该有
I think he mentioned a guitar.
我需要带吉他吗 还在吗
Do I need my guitar? Hello?
你好 我是来参加Cromartie先生的录音的 我叫Llewyn Davis
Hi, I'm here for Mr. Cromartie's session. Llewyn Davis.
坐吧 我会转告他的
Have a seat. I'll let him know you're here.
Llewyn
Llewyn.
Cromartie先生 很高兴见到你
Mr. Cromartie, it's an honor to meet you.
嘿 你的吉他呢
Heh. Where's your guitar?
嘿
Hey.
- 嘿 你来了  - 是的
- Hey, man, you made it.  - Yeah.
- 你要用吉普森吉他对吧  - 你的 好的
- You'll play a Gibson, right?  - Yours? Sure, yeah.
Martin被称为现代木吉他之王
Triple-O 21是其经典系列OOO 50年代时的一款
- 那你用...  - Triple-O 21 这位是Al cody
- You playing, uh...?  - Triple-O 21. Do you know Al Cody?
- 你好  - 嗨
- Hey, man. Hey.  - Hi.
你看识谱吗
Can you read a chart, Llewyn?
我
I, uh...
我可以盯着它装作看得懂
I can stare at a chart and fake it, sir.
好的 Jim和Al会教你唱那歌的
All right. Jim and Al will teach you the song.
慢慢来 我们是来享受的
Take your time. We're here to have fun.
好的
All right.
那么 我们
So we're, uh...?
我们是什么 John Glenn演唱组吗
We're the what? The John Glenn Singers?
这不是工作室之前常录的那种正儿八经的东西
It's not the most serious music we've recorded at this studio.
呃
Uh...
就是首歌
It's a thing.
*我不想去 别把我射到外太空去*
*I don't wanna Don't send me off into outer space*
*一到宇航服里我就满身是汗*
*I sweat when they put me*
*但我们想去...*
*Yeah, but we wanna go to...*
我们得把"P-P-please"唱进去
Let's still do the "P-p-please" Into the...
- 放进韵脚里  - 没开玩笑吧
- Into the verse.  - Really?
-是的  - P-p-p
- Yeah. - P-p-p
别把我射到外太空 P-p-p-p-please
Don't send me off into outer... P-p-p-p-please
什么 不行 我不
What? No, I ca...
它把韵脚都弄乱了
Because then it gets all muddled up into the verse.
- 不 不 不  - 发射
- No, no, no.  - Shoot.
不 你把"p-p-p"放到韵脚里 如果你只唱"p-p"
No, you just do the p-p-p's into the ver... If you do two p-p's.
-"P-p" 接着唱"一穿宇航服就满身是汗"  - 对
- P-p, then the "Sweat when they..."  - Yep.
- 真的  - 是的
- Really?  - Yep.
*P-p 我一穿上宇航服*
*P-p, I sweat when they stuck me*
*就浑身是汗*
*In the pressure suit*
*发射*
*Shoot.*
*太空头盔 飞侠戈登靴*
Bubble helmet Flash Gordon boots
*失重状态下*  *嗷呜 嗷呜 嗷呜*
*No air out there, gravity...*  *Ow, ow, ow*
*没想当英雄  *发射*
*That's no place to be a hero*  *Shoot.*
- 好的  - 对 哦 哦
- Okay. - Yeah. Oh-oh-oh.
好
Okay.
嘿 我很高兴在这儿演出 不过谁写的这歌
Hey, look, I'm happy for the gig, but who wrote this?
我写的
I did.
- 你  - 好了吗
- You...  - Okay?
好了吗
So okay?
- 好了  - 开始
- Good?  - Shoot.
"拜托 肯尼迪先生" 第一条 开录
"Please, Mr. Kennedy" Take one. And we're rolling.
一 二 一 二 三 四
One, two, one, two, three, four.
*十 九 八 七 六 五*
*Ten, nine Eight, seven, six, five*
*四 三 二 一*  *请等一下 *
*Four, three, two*  *One second, please*
*拜托 肯尼迪先生*  *嗷呜*
*Please, Mr. Kennedy*  *Uh-oh*
*我不想去*
*I don't wanna go*
*别把我射到外太空去*
*Please don't shoot me Into outer space*
*求求求你了*  *拜托 肯尼迪先生*
*P-p-please*  *Please, Mr. Kennedy*
*啊哦*  *我不想去*
*Uh-oh*  *I don't wanna go*
*别把我射到外太空去*
*Please don't shoot me Into outer space*
*我一穿上宇航服就浑身是汗*
*I sweat when they stuck me In the pressure suits*
*太空头盔 飞侠戈登靴*
*Bubble helmet Flash Gordon boots*
*失重状态下什么也没有*  *外太空*
*No air up there in gravity zero*  *Outer space*
*我想呼吸*  *外*
*I need to breathe*  *Outer*
*不想当英雄*  *太空*
*Don't need to be a hero*  *Space*
*你有没有清楚听到我的请求*
*Are you reading me loud and clear?*
*求你了 肯尼迪先生*  *啊哦*
*Oh, please, Mr. Kennedy*  *Uh-oh*
*我不想去*  *请别把我射到外太空去*
*I don't wanna go*  *Please don't shoot me into outer*
*拜托 肯尼迪先生*  *啊哦*
*Oh, please, Mr. Kennedy*  *Uh-oh*
*我不想去*
*I don't wanna go*
*请别把我射到外太空去*
*Please don't shoot me Into outer space*
*我身高一米八*
*I'm 6-foot-2*
*或许你可以教我*
*And so perhaps you'll*
*怎么窝在一米五几的航天舱里*
*Tell me how to fit into A 5-foot capsule*
*要是回地球时 我被烧成了灰*
*I won't be known As Man of the Century*
*我也不会成为世纪风云人物*
*If I'm blubbering upon reentry*
*家里有个撩人的妻子*  *外*
*Got a red-blooded wife*  *Outer*
*她需求旺盛*  *太空*
*With a healthy libido*  *Space*
*你会失去她的选票*  *外*
*You'll lose her vote - Outer*
*如果你让她成为寡妇*  *太空*
*If you make her a widow*  *Space*
*谁陪我们的孩子在后院玩捉迷藏*
*And who'll play catch Out in the back with our kid?*
*拜托了 肯尼迪先生*
*Oh, please, Mr. Kennedy*
*啊哦 我不想去*
*Uh-oh I don't wanna go*
*别把我射到外太空去*
*Please don't shoot me Into outer space*
*倒计时 十 九 八 七 六 五*
*Countdown, ten, nine Eight, seven, six, five*
*四 三 二*
*Four, three, two*
*哦不 哦*
*Oh, no Oh*
*拜托 肯尼迪先生 呜喔*
*Please, Mr. Kennedy Uh-oh*
*我不想去*
*I don't wanna go*
*求你别把我射到外太空去*
*Please don't shoot me Into outer space*
*拜托 拜托*
*Please Oh, please*
*拜托 别把我射到外太空去*
*Please Don't shoot me off into outer space*
*拜托了 肯尼迪先生*
*Oh! Please Mr. Kennedy*
*拜托 肯尼迪先生*
*Please Mr. Kennedy*
*求你别把我射到外太空去*
*Please don't shoot me Into outer space*
*拜托了 肯尼迪先生*
*Oh, please Mr. Kennedy*
不 谢谢你 我很感激
No, thank you. I appreciate it.
- 你知道的 我很需要这个  - 是的
- I needed this, as you know.  - Yeah.
噢
Oh...
- 我们有机会巡回演出的对吧  - 去哪 天王星嘛
- We'll be touring, right?  - Touring Uranus.
我会去接种疫苗的 签哪
I'll get my vaccinations. Sign where?
- 你是全美音乐联盟的成员吧  - 对
- You are AF of M, right?  - Yeah.
在这儿 还有这儿签一下
Sign there and there.
签唱片公司了吗
You don't have a label?
有 莱加西唱片公司
Uh, I do. Legacy.
哦 你是Mel的人
Oh, you're exclusive to Mel?
我需要一张许可证明 他会给你的
I'll need a permission. He'll give you one.
- 回头见  - 呃
- See you. - Uh...
那要好一会儿
That's gonna take...
不行 我现在亟需钱
Shit, man, I need the money now.
你如果不想成为员工 只想当签个单独合约的话
You wanna just be an independent contractor,
会计部今天就能给你支票
Accounting will give you a check today.
200美元的劳务费 这可是超出这一次的录音所值
Just bill us for services, $200. That's more than a session fee
因为你不拿版权费的
because you don't get royalties.
没问题 可以兑现了吗
Okay, that's fine. And I can cash it?
当然 就在拐角处
Sure, right around the corner.
但是你不再出现在录音名单上了 也就没版权了
But you don't go on a session sheet then, so no royalties.
无所谓 嘿 你住哪儿 AL
That's okay, that's fine. Hey, where do you live, Al?
- 唐宁街  - 好地方吗
- Downing Street. - Yeah, nice place?
- 垃圾一样的存在  - 呃 有沙发吗
- It's a dump.  - Uh-huh. Got a couch?
- Mel在哪儿  - 参加葬礼去了
- Where's Mel?  - Mel's at a funeral.
要命 那老家伙要参加的葬礼可真多
Boy, that man goes to a lot of funerals.
- 他喜欢交际  - 他认识的人一个个死去了
- He likes people.  - Fewer and fewer.
这次是家里人
This is family.
他的侄子 Georgie
His nephew, Georgie,
刚订婚 丈母娘就离世了
is engaged to a girl whose mother just passed.
那也算家人吗
I don't know if that's family.
他喜欢参加葬礼 我也不知道怎么和你说
He likes funerals. I don't know what to tell you.
我昨天被Mel气的都忘了拿信件了
I forgot to pick up my mail yesterday. I was so pissed at Mel.
你没忘
You didn't forget to pick up your mail.
- 不对 我忘了 - 你压根就没有信件
- Yeah, I did. - You don't have any mail.
哦
Oh.
靠
Shit.
芝加哥的Bud Grossman没有任何回信给我吗
I didn't get anything from Bud Grossman in Chicago?
应该有吗
You were supposed to get something from Bud Grossman?
对啊 我让Mel一出版我的独唱专辑就寄一张给他啊
Yeah, I had Mel send him my solo record when it came out.
- 差不多一个月前  - 哦
- Whenever, more than a month ago.  - Oh.
没有 你没收到什么信
No, you didn't get anything.
但是我们在给储货间腾地方
But we were making space in the stock room
把剩下来的旧唱片都扔了
and dumped the rest of the old records.
都是没人要的
All the remainders.
你的 还有Mikey的
Yours and Mikey's.
Mel把其中一个箱子留下了
Mel set one box aside.
想着你可能要保留些
Thought you might wanna keep some copies.
我要它们干嘛
What am I gonna do with them?
要我扔了么
Should I throw them out?
- 太好了  - 嘿
- Oh, good.  - Hey.
给你钥匙
Here's a key.
我正要去新泽西去取我妈的车呢
Just going out to Jersey to pick up my mom's car.
- 好的 哦 不好意思  - 哈哈哈
- Okay. Oh! Sorry. Okay. - Ha-ha-ha.
嗯嗯
Mm-hm.
- 哪位  - 嘿 是我 Llewyn
- Yeah?  - Hey, it's me, Llewyn.
- 什么事  - 我能上去吗
- Yeah?  - Can I come up?
不行
No.
好吧
Okay.
那啥
Well...
我能拿回我的东西吗
Well, can I have my stuff?
我会带下去的 在雷吉见
I'll bring it down. I'll meet you at the Reggie.
嘿
Hey.
谢了
Thank you.
- 今晚谁走狗屎运了  - 什么
- Who won the lottery tonight?  - Huh?
哦 我住在Al Cody那儿
Oh. I'm staying at Al Cody's.
你打算什么时候
So when do you wanna do the...?
- 去做  - 人流
- Have the...?  - The abortion?
越快越好
The sooner the better.
好的 我问问那家伙什么时候能做
Okay. I'll see when the guy can do it then.
我希望"那家伙"是个医生
"The guy"? I hope it's a doctor.
对对对 他是个医生
Yeah, yeah, yeah, he's a doctor.
- 你拿到钱了吗  - 有 拿到了 别担心
- You got the money?  - Yes, I have the money, don't worry.
- 和你共事 能不担心么  - 你不用这样的
- With you, I worry.  - Well, you shouldn't.
我必须用
Yes, I should.
老天都知道你啥也不干
God knows you never do.
从来都是推给别人 就像你避孕措施一样
You just let other people, like your method of birth control.
求你别再提双层避孕套的事了
Oh, please don't start with the double condoms again.
你有认真考虑过你的未来吗
Do you ever think about the future at all?
未来
The future?
你是说 像会飞的车那样的
You mean, like flying cars?
月球上开旅馆
Hotels on the moon?
- 唐  - 这就是为什么你永远都是一塌糊涂
- Tang?  - And this is why you're fucked.
不 这才是你一塌糊涂的原因
No, it's why you're fucked.
你总是构想着未来的蓝图
You're just trying to blueprint a future.
跟Jim一起搬到郊区 生孩子
Move to the suburbs with Jim, have kids.
- 那不好吗  - 如果音乐对你来说
- That's bad?  - If that's what music is for you,
只是达到这个目的的工具的话 那么是的 有点功利
a way to get to that place, then, yeah, it's a little careerist,
但也有些无聊
and it's a little square,
- 还有点悲哀  - 我悲哀
- and it's a little sad. - I'm sad?
一无所成的人可是你
You're the one who's not getting anywhere.
你没有想过要前进 而我和Jim有努力
You don't wanna get anywhere. Me and Jim try.
- 我有 我想  - 我们在努力 而你还在睡沙发
- I do. I wanna...  - We try, you sleep on the couch.
你这么说有点伤人啊
That's a bad thing to throw in my face.
你不想要前进
You don't wanna go anywhere.
这就是为什么麻烦事总会找上你
That's why all the same shit is gonna keep happening to you,
- 因为你想要这样  - 这是原因吗
- because you want it to.  - Is that why?
对 还因为你就是个混蛋
Yes, and also because you're an asshole
睡别人老婆的混蛋 别忘了这个
who sleeps with other people's women. Let's not forget that.
你在姑息自己 不是吗
You're being pretty kind to yourself now, aren't you?
今晚又去睡哪家的沙发
Whose couch are you on tonight?
我说过了 Al Cody的 你都不听
I told you. Al Cody's. You don't listen.
只是不停的奚落我
You just spout vitriol.
看着我的东西
Keep an eye on my shit.
别跑
Hey.
别跑 别跑 别跑
Hey. Hey, hey.
他妈的我真是个幸运的家伙
Oh, goddamn it. I am one lucky bastard.
谢谢你说来这地方
Thanks for suggesting this place.
小可怜从昨天开始就没吃过东西了
Poor thing couldn't have eaten since yesterday.
这可是只家猫 给你
It's a damn house cat. There you go.
你知道它的名字吗 我忘了他的名字
You know its name? I can't remember his name.
我不知道它的名字
I don't know its name.
我跟Gorfeins不是很熟
I don't hang out with the Gorfeins.
乖小猫 主啊 感谢老天
Oh, good kitty. Jesus, thank God.
我们说到哪了
Well, where were we?
你说我是个功利主义者 我说你是个废柴
You were calling me a careerist, and I was calling you a loser.
是的 那是你的分类方法
Right, well, those are your categories.
不 是你的分类方法
No, those are your categories.
在我看来
You know, in my experience,
这世界分为两种人
the world's divided into two kinds of people.
一种就是把世界分为两种人的人
Those who divide the world into two kinds of people...
还有废柴
And losers?
- 你好  - 你好
- Hey. - Hey.
你能帮我把这个拿上去吗 这里面没什么
Uh, can you bring this up for me? This ain't a spot.
- 我只是从家里拿点东西来  - 可以 当然可以
- I just brought some stuff from home. - Uh, yeah. Yeah, sure.
你不用 喵
Hey, you don't need to... Meow.
你不用在这里再多住几天吧 是吗
You don't need to crash for more than a couple days, do you?
我女朋友星期二从波士顿过来
My girlfriend's coming down from Boston on Tuesday.
对啊 不用
Uh... Yeah, no, that's...
对 不用 没事的 谢谢
Yeah, it's fine. That's okay. Yeah, thanks.
你想去芝加哥吗
You don't wanna go to Chicago, do you?
- 我为什么会想去芝加哥  - 对啊 哈哈
- Why would I wanna go to Chicago? - Yeah. Ha, ha.
这车星期二要去芝加哥
This car's going to Chicago Tuesday.
我的一个朋友要载个人
A friend of mine is taking someone
去演出 他们想找个人分摊油费
to a gig and they're looking for someone to help pay for gas.
我宁愿在纽约
I prefer New York.
谁是'Arthur Milgram'
Who's "Arthur Milgram"?
噢 是我
Oh, that's me.
我准备去登记改名 找个时间就去
I'm gonna change it legally, at some point.
Davis先生
Mr. Davis?
不不不 她不想我陪她
No, no, no, she won't want me with her.
好的 那她也要有个朋友陪着
Oh, okay. Well, she should have a friend though.
要有个人能陪她回去
Someone who can help her home.
- 好的 我会告诉她  - 只能在周六了
- Okay, I'll let her know.  - It'll have to be on a Saturday.
我能在周六做手术
Hey, I could do it this Saturday.
好的 我现在给你钱吧 因为我就不再来了 付现金
Okay. I'll, uh, pay you now since I won't see you. Cash.
噢 不不不
Oh! No, no, no. Heh.
- 不收费  - 啥
- No charge.  - Huh?
你知道的 上次
You know, from last time.
上次 你是说Diane
From last time? You mean Diane?
对 我没有你的号码和地址
Yeah, I didn't have a number or an address for you.
- 其实你到底住哪儿  - 等下 什么
- Where do you live anyway?  - Wait, what?
- 我没有  - 为什么
- I didn't have a...  - Why...?
- 为什么这次不收费  - 啥
- Why is there no charge this time?  - Huh?
为什么
Why...?
那个 你知道的啊
Well, you know.
不 我不知道 老兄 你现在在搞公益活动吗
Well, no, I don't know, man. You working pro bono now?
不 因为上次没有做
Well, no, since it didn't happen last time.
什么没有做
What didn't happen?
Diane没告诉你吗
Diane didn't tell you?
Diane没做流产手术
Diane did not terminate the pregnancy.
她来告诉我她决定
She came in to tell me she decided
生下来
to go to term.
她没告诉你吗
She didn't tell you?
没有
Uh, no.
她
She, uh...
天 她让我给她介绍个亚克朗市的医生
Geez, she asked me to refer her to a doctor in Akron.
- 亚克朗市  - 去接生
- In Akron?  - To deliver the, uh...
不 我知道她要去亚克朗市 她家就是亚克朗市的
No, I knew she was, uh, going to Akron. She's from Akron.
对
Yes.
- 抱歉 我以为  - 她父母就在亚克朗市
- I'm sorry, I thought...  - Her parents are in Akron.
那孩子现在大概两岁了吧
The kid would be about 2 now?
对 我猜是
Yeah, I guess.
对
Yes.
抱歉 我不知道怎么把钱退还给你
I'm sorry, I didn't know how to get the money back to you.
我再也没在"猫头鹰之声"(地名)看到你了
I never see you at the hoots anymore.
- 噢 猫回来了  - 对
- Oh, there's the cat. - Yeah.
野完回来了啊 嘿 Llewyn 欢迎 进来
Home from the hill. Hey, Llewyn, welcome. Come on in.
Lilian在厨房 她在做她最拿手的茄合
Lillian's in the kitchen. She's making her famous moussaka.
moussaka 茄合 肉和茄子做成的希腊菜
不 我不能打搅你们的晚餐 我只想
No, I can't barge in for dinner. I just wanted to...
- 不 不 来吧 多一个人而已  - 不 不 我不能这样
- No, no. Come on. One more person?  - No, no, no. No, I can't.
有茄合啊 来吧
Moussaka? Come on.
你知道 你知道Marty Green跟Janet Fung吗
Do you know, uh...? You know Marty Green and Janet Fung?
你好 很高兴看到你 Llewyn Davis
Hello, nice to meet you. Llewyn Davis.
噢 Mitch跟Lilian的民谣朋友
Oh, uh, Mitch and Lillian's, uh, folk song friend.
你要在这借宿吗
You crashing with us?
不不 不了 我本来都没打算吃晚餐呢
Oh, no, no, no. I hadn't even planned on dinner.
Llewyn不是上西城的人
Llewyn's not an Upper West Side guy.
要看到他 只能在
We only get to see him when...
在我找遍了我村里的朋友之后
When I've rotated through my Village friends.
对 我们是最后一家
Yeah, we're the last resort.
Marty是我的同事 Joe是个音乐家
Marty's in my department. And, uh, Joe's a musician.
这是Joe Flom 他是Lillian在音乐同好会里认识的
This is Joe Flom. He plays in Musica Anticha with Lillian.
你好 你怎么样
Oh, hello. How you doing?
- 很高兴遇到你  - 嗯
- Nice to meet you. - Yes.
你玩什么乐器
What's your instrument?
只要有键盘的都玩
Well, anything with a keyboard.
我在MA里玩风琴和大键琴
I play celeste and harpsichord in MA.
多数时候 我是个钢琴教师
I'm a piano instructor most days.
- 有烟吗  - 当然
- Hey, bum a cigarette?  - Oh, sure.
要杯酒吗 Llewyn
Glass of wine, Llewyn?
- 要点低级红酒  - 对
- A little dago red? - Yeah.
我应该带点什么来的
I should've brought something.
别傻了 你把猫带回来了啊
Hey, don't be silly, you brought the cat.
是 对
Yeah, right.
那个
You know, uh,
我以前小时候上过钢琴课
I used to, uh, take piano lessons when I was a kid
Sieglestein夫人教的
from, uh, Mrs. Sieglestein.
你知道Sieglestein夫人吗
You don't know Mrs. Sieglestein, do you?
很粗很粗的小腿 穿着矫正鞋
Very, very big calves, orthopedic shoes,
住在远洛克威 库尔兰酒店的楼上
lives in Far Rockaway, upstairs from the Kurlands?
她弹早期的作品吗
Does she play early music?
这个
Um...
广播里的Harry James
Harry James on the radio.
Harry James  早期的音乐家 演员
钢琴方面
On the piano, um,
"饮我与君目"
"Drink to Me Only with Thine Eyes."
英国早期歌曲 歌词出自Ben Jonson1616年的诗<Song To Celia>
嗯
Uh-huh.
她不是个赶时髦的人
She was not a swinger.
但她弹Harry James啊
Well, Harry James.
也是 对 她弹得还挺好听的
Okay, yeah, well, her playing that was pretty on the beat.
他很可爱
He's adorable.
- 他多大了  - 四月就满两岁了
- How old is he?  - Just turned 2 in April.
他现在跟我妈妈在一起
He's with my mother now.
祖母们总会派上用场的 对吧
Grandmas come in handy, right?
- 他叫什么名字  - Howie
- What's his name?  - Howie.
他都开始叫他Howie了 是Howard
He already calls him Howie. It's Howard.
Howie Greenfung
Howie Greenfung.
什么 像是
What? Like...?
像是'Green-fung'吗 带个横杠的
Like, "Green-fung"? Hyphenated?
不不 就一个字 Greenfung
No, no, one word, Greenfung.
Howard Greenfung
Howard Greenfung.
你在逗我吗
You're kidding, right?
- 不  - Llewyn 你不如
- No. - Llewyn, why don't you...?
不如你给我们唱首歌吧
Why don't you give us a song?
对了 拜托了 他唱歌真的很好
Oh, yes, please. He's very good.
- Joe应该听一下  - 不
- Joe should hear you.  - No.
- 还有Marty和Janet  - 当然
- And Marty and Janet.  - Of course.
我去拿我的Silvertone吉他
I'm getting my Silvertone.
Silvertone 吉他品牌 被称为美国吉他界的一面旗帜
只要你唱的话 就能给你弹一下
You get to play it if and only if you sing.
行了 好了 好了
Right, yeah, okay, I can tell
我只能说现在我不停拒绝
this is one of those things where I keep saying no
而你们以为我在让你们呼声再热烈点
and you think I'm just asking you to beg more.
对 就是这样
Yeah, that's right.
听着 我不是训练过的狗一样任人摆布
Hey, look, I'm not a trained poodle.
我觉得唱歌是灵魂表达愉悦的一种方式
I thought singing was a joyous expression of the soul.
对
Yeah.
好了
All right. Um...
这是
This is...
这是早期的 Joe应该会喜欢
This one's early. Joe should like it.
*如果我有双翅*
*If I had wings*
*如诺亚身旁的白鸽*
*Like Norah's dove*
*我会飞越河流*
*I'd fly up the river*
*飞到我的所爱*
*To the one I love*
*别了*  *了*
*Fare thee well*  *Well*
*哦 我的爱人*  *啊 我的爱人*
*Oh, honey...*  *Oh, honey...*
- 你在干什么  - 什么
- What are you doing?  - What?
那是怎么了 你在干什么
What is that? What are you doing?
- 这是Mike的部分  - 别这样
- Well, it's Mike's part.  - Don't do that.
- 这是Mike的部分  - 我知道 别这样
- It's Mike's part. - I know what it is. Don't do that.
是吗 你知道吗 这太扯了
Oh, you know what? This is bullshit.
对不起 这是 我不做这个 好吗
I'm sorry, this is... I don't do this, okay?
我唱歌是为了谋生的 不是
I do this for a living. It's not a...
不是个他妈的室内游戏
it's not a fucking parlor game.
Llewyn 拜托 这对Lillian不公平
Llewyn, please, that's unfair to Lillian.
这太扯了 我又没说要来吃晚饭
This is bullshit. I don't ask you over for dinner
然后建议你
and then suggest you give
做个什么中美洲人的演讲
a lecture on the peoples of Mesoamerica.
或是关于什么前哥伦比亚时期
Or whatever your pre-Columbian shit is.
这是我的工作 这是我用来交租的工具
This is my job. This is how I pay the fucking rent.
Llewyn 这不是...
Llewyn, that's not...
这是个有爱的家
This is a loving home.
我他妈的是专业的 还有 你知道吗
I'm a fucking professional. And you know what?
- 让Mike的部分去死吧  - 啊
- Fuck Mike's part!  - Ah!
- 没事 Lillian  - 只是 只是
- It's okay, Lillian.  - This is just a... This is...
我不能待在这里 我不能待在这里
I can't stay in this room. I can't stay in this room.
那个 她
Well, she...
她不用走 很明显 我会走
She doesn't have to leave. I'm leaving, obviously.
很抱歉 我搞砸了你的晚餐
Sorry I fucked up your evening.
- 谢谢招待的茄合  - 啊
- Thank you for the moussaka.  - Aah!
这不是我们的猫
This is not our cat.
什么 这当然是你们的猫
What? Of course that's your cat.
- 天哪  - 这都不是公的
- Oh, my God.  - It's not even male.
阴囊在哪 Llewyn
Where's its scrotum, Llewyn?
- 那个 它  - 阴囊在哪
- Wh... it's... - Where's its scrotum?
我的东西
My stuff.
你好
Hello.
嗯 嗨
Yeah, hey.
这是什么
What's this?
我的吉他
It's my guitar.
当然 拿进来吧 别管我
Sure, move in. Don't mind me.
你爱哪样哪样
Make yourself at home.
你干嘛的 跳弗拉明戈的吗
What are you, a flamenco dancer?
叫什么名字 Pablo
What's your name? Pablo?
Llewyn Davis
Llewyn Davis.
我是Roland Turner
I am Roland Turner.
这是我的男仆 Johnny Five
This is my valet, Johnny Five.
Johnny Five
Johnny Five.
那是我最后一次在莫非斯堡
And that was the last time I was in Murfreesboro.
我知道他们都不欢迎我再回去
Gave me to understand I would not be welcome back.
我说'行了 兄弟 我不会
I said, "That's okay, brother. I might have managed on my own
让自己再回来你这鸟不拉屎的小镇'
not to make it back to your little flyspeck horseshit town."
N代表什么
What the N stand for?
- 什么  - N代表的是什么
- What?  - What's the N stand for?
- Lou N Davis  - 'Llewyn'
- Lou N. Davis.  - "Llewyn."
Llewyn L L E W Y N 是威尔士文
Llewyn, L-L-E-W-Y-N. It's Welsh.
好吧 这世上肯定有些
Well, it would have to be something,
听着就傻屌白痴的名字
stupid fucking name like that.
- 你不像是威尔士人  - 我母亲是意大利人
- You don't look Welsh-  - My mother was Italian...
你应该会对这个感兴趣
Here, this would interest you.
当时我跟Johnny在西雅图的"高点"咖啡馆表演
Johnny and I were in Seattle playing the High Spot.
还记得吗 Johnny
Remember this, Johnny?
我吃了个烤芝士吐司后就开始不舒服
And I became indisposed after eating a toasted cheese sandwich,
身上每个孔都在排泄
and found myself purging from every orifice,
拉的像消防管一样
one of them like a fire hose.
我问经理
I said to the manager:
"我刚吃的叫什么"
"What do you call that thing I just ate?"
他说是"威尔士干酪"
He said, "Welsh rarebit."
我说"那么 威尔士产的所有东西都会让人变成一坨屎吗
I says, "Okay, does everything from Wales make you shit yourself,
还是只有这吐司会呢"
or just this piece of toast?"
他说... 老天啊 这是什么啊
He said... Holy Jesus. What is that thing?
这 这是我的猫 其实 这不是我的猫 这
It's... It's my cat. Well, it's not my cat, it's...
大男人与猫
Grown man with a cat.
- 这也是艺术吗  - 不
- Is that part of your act?  - No.
- 你刚说你玩什么的  - 民谣
- What'd you say you played?  - Folk songs.
民谣 我还以为你是个音乐家呢
Folk songs. Thought you said you were a musician.
带着猫的民谣歌手 你是基的吗
Folk singer with a cat. You queer?
这 这不是我的猫 我只是不知道要拿它怎么办
L... It's not my cat. I just didn't know what to do with it.
是吗 那你也有带你的小弟弟来吧
Really? So did you bring your dick along too?
Johnny 停车
Johnny, hold up.
这有个服务区
There's a service station.
轮到你给油钱了 Elwin
Your turn to pay for gas, Elwin.
他还在里面吗
He still in there?
你是Al的朋友
You're a friend of Al's?
对
Yeah.
*当我回到巴尔的摩*
*When I go back Baltimore*
*地板上再也不需要铺地毯*
*Need no carpet on my floor*
*来吧 跟着我*
*Come along and follow me*
*我们前往加利利*
*We'll go down to Galilee*
*一起来*
*Everybody*.
*翠绿翠绿的石板路*
*Green, green, rocky road*
*就是这样*
*Yeah.*
*在翠绿中漫步*
*Promenade in green*
*嗯 嗯*
*Mm-hm.*
*谁是你的爱 谁是你的爱*
*Tell me who you love Tell me who you love*
*很好*
*Nice.*
那里有个标志写着"不准扎杆击球 不准使用硬币辅助"
There was a sign that said, "No masse shots, no coins on cloth."
我说"那允许我把球从台边上
I said, "Am I allowed to bank
垫起来吗 还是说太招摇了"
the ball off the cushions or is that too fancy?"
那家伙说"你是个骗子" 我说"去你妈的白痴
The guy says, "You're a hustler." I say, "You're a fucking idiot.
想骗你钱才不会充内行呢
A hustler pretends he's out of his depth.
我跟你说我是内行的 可能你才是骗子
I'm telling you I'm an adept. Maybe you're the hustler
在那边装傻来骗我"
pretending to be a lunkhead. Got me fooled."
"不准扎杆击球 不准使用硬币辅助 "
"No mass in shots, no coins on cloth."
不要约束我 想弹什么弹什么
Don't give me rules. You play what you play.
当然 你可能不行 但爵士乐的话 我们每个音符都弹
Well, you don't, but in jazz, you know, we play all the notes.
一个节里就有十二个音符的 蠢蛋 可不是那种弱智的夏威夷四弦琴
Twelve notes in a scale, dipshit, not three chords on a ukulele.
G调 g调 c调 g调
G, g, c, g
C调 d调 g调
C, d, g
如果你要以此谋生 祝你好运
Well, if you make a living at it, more power to you.
单人演出
Solo act?
- 对 现在是  - 现在
- Yeah, now.  - Now?
以前是怎样 跟猫一起表演吗
Used to, what, work with the cat?
你弹一次C大调 他就吐个小毛团吗
Every time you play a C major, he'd puke a hair ball?
我以前有个搭档
I used to have a partner.
后来呢
What happened?
他从乔治华盛顿大桥跳下来了
He threw himself off the George Washington Bridge.
我去 我不怪他
Well, shit, I don't blame him.
换了我也不能忍受
I couldn't take it either,
每晚都要弹'Jimmy Cracked Corn'
having to play "Jimmy Cracked Corn" Every night.
Jimmy Cracked Corn 美国儿歌
噢 原谅我这么说
Oh, pardon me for saying so,
但这他妈的也太蠢了吧 不是吗
that's pretty fucking stupid, isn't it?
乔治华盛顿大桥
George Washington Bridge?
一般的话 都是从布鲁克林大桥跳的吧
You throw yourself off the Brooklyn Bridge, traditionally.
乔治华盛顿大桥
George Washington Bridge?
谁会这样做啊
Who does that?
他干嘛了 白痴吗
What was he, a dumbbell?
也不是
Not really.
你就在那时候捡到这猫的吗
And that's when you picked up the cat?
听着 牛仔音乐家 你会对这个感兴趣的
Here, Cowboy Chords, this would interest you.
我在瑞士蒙特勒看过这个
There's this act I saw in Montreux, Switzerland.
一个贝斯 一台钢琴
A bass, a piano and a sound tree...
Turner先生 我在想
Hey, Mr. Turner, I'm wondering.
- 啥  - 用那根手杖
- Huh?  - Would that cane
捅你屁眼是能完全进去呢
fit all the way up your ass
还是会剩一点出来啊
or would a little bit stay sticking out?
好
Okay.
好吧
恐吓什么的对我没用
Except threats and intimidation won't work with me.
想知道原因吗 你可能会觉得很有趣
You wanna know why? This would interest you.
我学习过萨泰里阿教
I studied Santeria
萨泰里阿教 非洲部落和天主教的结合
以及其它一些东西
and certain other things
你们这些凡夫俗子理解不了就管它们叫巫术
that squares like you would call the black arts
我在新奥尔良时跟Chano Pozo学的
due to lack of understanding, from Chano Pozo in New Orleans.
Chano Pozo 古巴非裔爵士打击乐音乐家 拉丁爵士的奠基人  后来皈依了萨泰里阿教
你说你会整垮我
You say you'll mess me up?
我根本无需把这些幼稚的威胁说出口
I don't have to make those childish threats.
我只要稍微动一动 然后你就会在某天醒来的时候想
I do my thing, and one day you wake up wondering:
"我侧边的肋骨怎么这么痛"
"Why do I have this pain in my side?"
或者不是那么具体的事
Or maybe it won't even be that specific.
你只是觉得 "我为什么事事不顺呢
Maybe it's, "Why is nothing going right for me?
我的生活就是一大碗屎
My life is a big bowl of shit.
我怎么就混成这副屎样了呢"
I don't remember making this big bowl of shit."
与此同时 Roland Turner在千里之外
Meantime, Roland Turner is a thousand miles away,
笑尿了
laughing his ass off.
想想那副情形 Elwin
Think about that, Elwin.
在这辆车里 蛮横无礼是行不通的
In this car, bad manners won't work.
借根烟
Bum a cigarette?
我没了
I'm out.
"干净的混蛋之歌"
"Clean Asshole Poems,"
Orlovsky
Orlovsky.
Orlovsky 彼得 奥洛夫斯基 美国诗人 演员 这首诗原名<干净的混蛋和微笑的蔬菜之歌>
然后
Then,
出演了
acted.
<禁闭室>
The Brig.
<禁闭室> 上世纪60年代讲述海军陆战队监狱暴行的超现实主义戏剧
表演了三个星期
Three weeks on that show.
本来还能再久一点
Could've been more.
结果被条子封了
Cops closed it.
怎么会
How come?
说来话长
Long story.
还要 还要 床喊道
"'More, more, more, 'cried the bed.
<干净的混蛋之歌>节选
还要为我说更多
'Talk to me more.'
哦 床啊撑着世界的重量
Oh, bed that faked The weight of the world.
所有失去的梦都压在你身上
All the lost dreams laid on you.
哦 床啊不长毛发
Oh, bed that grows no hair.
不会挨操
That cannot be fucked,
或者会挨操
or can be fucked.
哦 床啊世世代代的残渣是你的支柱
Oh, bed crumbs of all ages Spilled on you.
哦 床啊
Oh, bed.
很好
Yes.
呃...
Well...
恕我失陪
Excuse me.
嗨
Hi.
这里离芝加哥还有多远
How far are we from Chicago?
大概三个小时 取决于天气咯
About three hours, a little more with the weather.
需要我叫辆救护车吗
Should I go call an ambulance?
不用了 他好着呢
No, he's all right.
拿着他的手杖
Grab his sticks.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
- 我只是 呃...  - 你不能在这里停车
- I'm just, uh...  - You can't stop here.
我只是停下来稍微休息一下
I just pulled over to rest a little bit.
你喝高了
You inebriated?
- 他没醉  - 我没问你
- He's not drunk. - I wasn't talking to you.
你 下车
You, get out of the car.
- 我吗   - 你 下车
- Me?  - You. Out of the car.
过来 你这样走走看...
Come here, I want you to walk...
- 别碰我  - 别耍花样 小子
Hands off the merchandise.  - Don't play games, kid.
婊子养的
Son of a bitch.
- 我们走  - 哼
- Let's go.  - Yeah.
我在你们所谓的监狱里呆过 没用的我告诉你
I've been in your jails. That's not gonna work.
该死
Shit.
哦 该...
Oh, sh...
二号
Number two.
- 续点咖啡  - 好的
- More coffee? - Yeah.
我们要换班了 能请您结下账吗
We're switching over. Could you pay the ticket?
你在等哪趟车
What train are you waiting for?
应验之梦
后台门
有人吗
Hello?
Bud Grossman在吗
Is Bud Grossman here?
还没来
Isn't in yet.
我能在这里等一下吗
Can I wait here?
呃 当然 大概要等一个小时
Uh, sure. Maybe an hour.
感觉可卡因在我脑子里乱窜
Cocaine Runnin' all around my brain
Grossman先生
Mr. Grossman.
嗯
Yeah?
我 呃...我是Llewyn Davis
I, uh... I'm Llewyn Davis.
啊哈
Uh-huh.
- 恕我冒昧 您知道我吗  - 不知道
- I'm sorry, do you know me? - No.
呃 Mel Novikoff一个月前给您寄了我的唱片
Um, Mel Novikoff sent you my record about a month ago.
- Llewyn Davis的心声  - 哦 你认识Mel
- Inside Llewyn Davis. - Oh, you're with Mel.
是的 是 我刚到呃...芝加哥
Yeah, yeah, I was, uh, just in Chicago,
刚巧路过
just, uh... Just passing through.
呃...
Um...
- 您喜欢那张唱片吗  - 不知道 我没收到你的唱片
- You like the record?   - Don't know. I didn't get it.
那 呃
Well, um,
我这里有 它是...
here it is. Uh, it's...
就是这张 它
This is it anyway, it's...
5块钱
That'll be $5.
开个玩笑
I was joking.
啊哈
Uh-huh.
呃 那个 我 呃
Well, yeah, I'm, um...
我希望能在这里演出
I'm interested in gigging here,
但 呃 也希望您能签下我
but, um, maybe also in obtaining management.
啊哈
Uh-huh.
Mel给你钱了吗
You getting any money out of Mel?
- 还没...  - 嗯 我就知道
- Not...  - Yeah, I bet.
好了 我们来听点东西吧
Okay, let's hear something.
您不打算听听唱片么
You don't wanna hear the record?
为什么要听 你人就在这儿 直接演奏点儿什么吧
Why should I? You're here. Play me something.
从Llewyn Davis之声里
Play me something from
挑一个表演给我看看
Inside Llewyn Davis.
好 好的 在这里 还是舞台上
Okay. All right. Here? Stage?
不在这儿
Not here.
好的
Okay.
*Jane王后躺在产室里*
*Queen Jane lay in labor*
*已有九天九夜多*
*Full nine days or more*
*直到她的女仆精疲力尽*
*Till her women grew so tired*
*再也无力支撑*
*They could no longer there*
*国王Henry 国王Henry*
*King Henry, King Henry*
*能否求您为我做件事*
*Will you do one thing for me?*
*能否求您剖开我的右腹*
*Will you open my right side*
*取出我的宝贝*
*And find my baby?*
*哦 不行 国王Henry饮泣 *
*"Oh, no," Cried King Henry*
*那件事我永远不会去做*
*"That's a thing I never can do*
*如果要我失去英格兰之花*
*If I lose the flower of England*
*我宁愿一并失去她的枝叶*
*I shall lose the branch too*
*I shall lose the branch too"*
*人们载歌载舞*
*There was fiddlin' and dancin'*
*在小王子出生的那天*
*On the day the babe was born*
*但可怜的王后Jane*
*But poor Queen Jane*
*我深爱的*
*Beloved*
*躺在那里石块般冰冷*
*Lay cold as a stone*
我看不出太大的商业价值
I don't see a lot of money here.
好吧
Okay.
好吧 所以就这样了
Okay. So that's it?
你还行 不算新手
You're okay. You're not green.
但是我缺少 比如说 Troy Nelson有的东西吗
But I don't have what, say, Troy Nelson has?
你知道Troy
You know Troy?
好孩子
Good kid.
他是个好孩子
He's a good kid.
是的
Yeah.
他能引发人们的共鸣
He connects with people.
听着 我在筹备一个三人组合 两男一女
Look, I'm putting together a trio. Two guys and a girl singer.
你当不了首唱
You're no front guy,
但是如果你愿意修剪下胡子 留成山羊胡子
but if you can cut that down to a goatee,
不抛头露面
and stay out of the sun,
我们可以让你试试你的声音能不能合上那两个人
we might see how your voice works with the other two.
你愿意做和声吗
You comfortable with harmonies?
不
No.
愿意 但是 呃 算了
Yes. But, um, no.
算了 我有过搭档
No, I had a partner.
啊哈 那就讲得通了
Uh-huh. Well, that makes sense.
我的建议
MY Suggestion?
你们重组
Get back together.
好建议
That's good advice.
谢谢你 Grossman
Thank you, Mr. Grossman.
- 你去哪儿  - 纽约
- Where you going?  - New York.
太好了伙计 我回新泽西的家 眼都没合过
Man, that's great. I'm going home to New Jersey. I've not slept.
- 你会开车 对吗  - 嗯
- You drive, right?  - Yeah.
那好 你能开多久尽量开多久 让我睡一会儿
Well, as long as you drive and let me sleep,
我们换着一路开回家
we can do it all the way, man.
我去 该...
Oh, sh...
那么 呃 我能随船出海吗
So, uh, can I ship out?
不 你不能
No, you cannot.
- 为什么  - 因为你不在名册上
- Why?  - You're not on the roster.
好吧 那你能把我加到名册上吗
Okay. Well, can you put me on the roster?
不 我不能
No, I cannot.
- 为什么  - 你说为什么
- Why?  - Why you think?
我不清楚 因为我是共产主义
I don't know. Because I'm a Communist.
- 不入流的苏联作风  - 什么
- Shachtmanite?  - What?
Shachtmanite 马克思主义Marxism和美马克思主义者Max Shachtman的结合体 主要讽刺斯大林主义 官僚集体主义的前苏联
不 你不是 你不是 呃
No, you ain't that. You ain't, uh...
- 你不是现役  - 我不是现役
- You ain't current.  - I'm not current?
- 这是另一种说法  - 海上术语吗
- That's another way of putting it.  - Is that a nautical term?
你的会费已经逾期未交了
You ain't current on your dues.
你把欠款还上 148刀
You pay your dues, arrears, 148 bucks,
就能回到名册上 我就能让你随船出海
you go back on the roster and I can ship you out.
"门外的少女"船上有个位置 要一级水手
There's a post on The Maid of the Gate, Seaman First Class.
这周五晚上6点起航
She weighs anchor this Friday, 6 p.M.
我欠的那钱能不能
The money, what I owe, can't
从我第一周的不管什么工钱里面扣呢
they just take it out of, whatever, the first week?
我又赖不掉 我到时候肯定在你们该死的沙丁鱼罐头里待着
I can't run out on it. I'm in your fucking sardine can.
是 不过他们不允许这样做 想随船出海你就必须是现役
Yeah, they don't do that. You gotta be current to ship out.
哇哦
Wow.
我才挣到手的钱 我要净身出海了 伙计
I just make it. I'm leaving naked, man.
- 从零开始 好了 现在能直接付给你吗  - 嗯哼
- Clean start. Okay. Can I pay you?  - Mm-hm.
好 我给你写张收据
Now, I will write you a receipt,
顺便写上码头 船号还有时间
along with the, uh, pier, ship number, and the time.
你的大副和舵手证还在吧
Got your Masters Mate's and Pilot's license, right?
- 没有他们你可不能出海  - 嗯 还在
- You ain't shipping out without that. - Yeah, I got it.
好了给你 Llewyn Davis
There you go, Llewyn Davis.
嘿 你不是Hugh Davis的儿子 对吧
Hey, you're not Hugh Davis's kid, are you?
为什么不是
Why not?
嘿
Hey...
最近好吗
How's it going?
我要出海了 爸爸
I'm taking off, Pop.
一段时间里都见不到了
Won't see you for a while.
随船出海
Shipping out.
尝试点新东西
Try something new.
也可以说重操旧业
I mean something old.
好了
Okay.
这个 我给你弹首你过去喜欢的
Here's this. You used to like this.
*哦 爽朗又宜人的天气*
*Oh, it was a fine And a pleasant day*
*我出海离开港口雅茅斯*
*Out of Yarmouth Harbor I was faring*
*在航行的小帆船上做侍童*
*As a cabin boy On a sailing lugger*
*一同去打捞鲜活肥美的鲱鱼群*
*For to hunt The bonny shoals of herring*
*现在你已在甲板上*
*Now you're up on deck*
*你是个渔民*
*You're a fisherman*
*你要展示男子汉气概你发誓*
*You can swear And show a manly bearing*
*和其他小伙子一起轮班监视*
*Take your turn and watch With the other fellas*
*直到你捕到了鲜活肥美的鲱鱼群*
*As you hunt The bonny shoals of herring*
*你说 我自己挣来衣食住行钱*
*Well, I earned my keep And I paid my way*
*我自己把一身行头挣来*
*And I earned the gear That I was wearing*
*我航行了一百万英里*
*I sailed a million miles*
*我捕了一千万条鱼*
*Caught 10 million fishes*
*我们梦到大群的*
*We were dreaming Of the shoals*
*鲱鱼*
*Of herring*
*日夜我们在海上勇敢前行*
*Night and day The seas we're darin'*
*无论风浪或平静*
*Come wind or calm*
*亦或是冬天的狂风*
*Or winter gale*
*无论出汗或寒冷*
*Sweating or cold*
*长大 老去*
*Growing up, growing old*
*或行将死去*
*Or dying*
*我们梦想着大群的*
*As we dream about The shoals*
*鲱鱼*
*Of herring*
哇哦
Wow.
不好意思
Excuse me?
能麻烦你一下吗 我爸爸他 呃
Could I trouble you? My father had, um...
他需要清洁
He needs to be cleaned.
他怎么样
How is he?
挺好的
He's great.
我看到我想看的了
Good to see what I have to look forward to.
什么
What?
- Llewyn  - 我没在开玩笑
- Llewyn.  - No, I'm not kidding.
我现在把问题都解决了
I got it all figured out now.
你操劳了这么些年
You put in some hard years,
是的 不过最终都会得到回报
yeah, but eventually you get to kick back,
食物端到嘴边 拉屎都不用动一下
your food's brought to you, don't even have to get up to shit.
- Llewyn Danny就在这儿坐着呢  - 哦 抱歉
- Llewyn, Danny's sitting right here.  - Oh, sorry.
你发什么神经 替你害臊
What's wrong with you? Shame on you.
对不起 见到他真高兴 一切都很好
I'm sorry. It was really good to see him. It was great.
- 你把我的文件箱放哪里了  - 哈
- Where'd you put my file box?  - Huh?
从那个房子里拿回来的 我的文件箱在哪儿
From the house, where's my file box?
你说让我把东西都扔了
You told me to throw everything out.
所有的东西吗 Joy
All the old shit, Joy.
- 靠 你把我的文件箱扔了  - Llewyn
- Fuck, you threw out my file box?  - Llewyn.
是 不说脏话 但现在例外
Yeah, no cursing. Except
我他妈现在不得不再去一趟该死的工会大厦
now I gotta go back to the fucking union hall.
因为我要去补办大副和舵手证
It had my Masters Mate's and Pilot's license in it.
我的老天 Joy
Jesus Christ, Joy.
是你告诉我把他们扔到大街上的
You told me to put it out by the curb.
我只是照办而已
It's what I did.
你走 马上从这里滚出去
I want you to leave. Get out of here.
靠
Fuck.
- 是 我就是个混蛋 怎样  - 一点儿没错
- Yeah, I'm a dick, right?  - That's right.
Danny 你舅舅是个坏人
Danny, your uncle's a bad man.
知道了
Okay.
- 你好  - Llewyn 别挂断
- Hello?  - It's Llewyn. Don't hang up.
我不打算留下来 我只需要一个地方放我的东西 拜托
I don't wanna stay. I just need a place to dump my stuff. Please.
我实在没劲儿随身拎着它了
I'm tired of dragging it all around with me.
好吗
Please?
- 你准备去哪儿待着  - 我不知道
- Where are you gonna stay?  - I don't know.
只需要两个晚上
It's only two nights.
五个街区肯定能找到
There must be someone in
一个没被我惹毛的人
the five boroughs who isn't pissed at me.
- 你感觉怎么样  - 很好啊
- How do you feel? - Fine.
怎么了
Why?
就是那件事很顺利了
So it went okay?
我星期六才做手术
I'm doing it Saturday.
老天 Llewyn 你他妈根本连记都不记得
Jesus, Llewyn, you don't even fucking remember.
是 对不起 我出去了一趟
Yeah, boy, I'm sorry. I... I was away.
感觉过了很久的样子
Well, it seemed like it was a long time,
其实不过几天而已 是啊
but it was just a couple of days. Yeah.
- 嗯对不起  - 你去哪儿了
- Yeah, I'm sorry. - Where were you?
芝加哥
In Chicago.
为什么去那儿
Why?
没 没事
No. Nothing.
Pappi明天让你演出
Pappi will let you play tomorrow.
挣点儿钱
Pick up a couple bucks.
不 他不会 我不到一个月之前才在那里干过
No, he won't. I was there less than a month ago.
他会的 我拜托过他了
He will. I asked him.
哇哦 谢谢你 你这样做实在是太好了
Wow. Thank you, that was very nice of you,
但是我不干了 不玩音乐了
but I'm out. I'm done.
- 我打算回到商船上去  - 什么 就这样了吗
- Going back to the Merchant Marine. - What, that's it?
明天的演出对你有好处的
This could be good for you tomorrow.
在煤气灯俱乐部表演第四百次
Playing the Gaslight for the 400th time?
就为了那一点小钱
For the fucking basket?
实际上 就那一点钱还要和别人分
Actually, you'd have to split the basket.
- 嘿  - 还有别人要表演
- Heh.  - There's another act.
<时代周刊>的人要去
But The Times is gonna be there.
哦 <时代周刊>
Oh, The Times.
对不起
I'm sorry.
抱歉 谢谢你的好意
I'm sorry. Thanks for the thought,
但是也不会有什么结果的
but it's not going anywhere.
我累了
I'm tired.
你累了吗
You're tired?
是 我太他妈累了
Yeah, I'm so fucking tired.
我想我只需要好好的睡一觉 但是还是...
I thought I just needed a night's sleep, but it's...
可能还不够
It's more than that.
但是谢谢你 谢谢你的尝试
But thank you, for trying.
我爱你
I love you.
拜托
Come on.
你在开什么玩笑
Are you shitting me?
怎么说 伙计
In what way, buddy?
85美金 就为了补办一张证
Eighty-five dollars? To replace a license?
证件你怎么能乱扔呢
You don't throw out the license.
那是需要你好好保管的东西
That's the one thing you keep.
我不行...让我到哪里...
I can't... Where am I gonna...?
靠
Fuck.
那好吧 你把这个钱退给我吧
All right, well, let me get this money back then.
我有...
I got...
我还拿着这玩意儿呢
I kept this fucking thing.
我今天早上刚还了欠款148美金 这是收据
I just paid my dues this morning, 148 bucks. There's the receipt.
你不能...
You don't...
会费我们是不退还的 你白痴吗
We don't pay dues back. What are you, nuts?
我今天早上才交的 就四个小时之前
I just paid it this morning. That was four hours ago.
- 是啊  - 拜托 你是说
- Yeah.  - Come on, you're telling me...
我既不能上船 也不能把我的钱要回来
I can't crew the ship, and I can't get this money back?
那钱是你欠工会的
This was money you owed your union.
你是Hugh Davis的小孩儿吗
You Hugh Davis's kid?
- 是啊  - 他怎么样
- Yeah. - How's he doing?
他好着呢 事实上他还一直问候你来着
He's fucking great. Matter of fact, he's been asking after you.
*饥饿的感觉*
*A hungry feelin'*
*悄悄来袭*
*Came o'er me stealin'*
*老鼠发出尖利的叫声*
*And the mice were squealin'*
*在我小小的监牢*
*In my prison cell*
*然后那块古旧的铁三角*
*And the auld triangle*
*叮咚叮咚作响*
*Went jingle jangle*
*沿着皇家运河的*
*All along the banks*
*两岸*
*Of the Royal Canal*
*开始新的清晨*
*To begin the morning*
*一个狱卒开始大喊*
*A screw was bawlin'*
*起床了...*
*Get up...*
嘿
Hey.
明天就能欣赏到你的表演了
We're gonna hear you tomorrow.
嗯 我想是的
Yeah, I guess you are.
欢迎你
Well, you're welcome.
你觉得这些家伙怎么样
What do you think of these guys?
*沿着皇家运河的*
*All along the banks*
*两岸*
*Of the Royal Canal*
我喜欢他们的毛衣
I like the sweaters.
*那些家伙们还在睡*
*The lads were sleepin'*
你根本不能相信这里的租金贵得多离谱
You know, you wouldn't fucking believe the rent here.
这些狗屁民谣 我才不了解
This folk shit, I don't know.
我们有一对好观众 Jim和Jean
Jim and Jean, we get a good crowd.
知道原因吗 Llewyn
You know why, Llewyn?
这些家伙的大部分
Lot of these guys,
他们大部分来这儿看演出
a lot them come in here catch the act,
都是因为他们想上Jean
because they wanna fuck Jean.
所以他们才来
That's why they come in.
然后还有一些人 还有一些伙计 Llewyn
And some of them, some of these guys, Llewyn,
他们来是因为他们想上Jim
they come in here because they wanna fuck Jim.
他们想上Jim
They wanna fuck Jim.
懂我的意思吗
Know what I mean?
- 你是说他们想操Jim  - 正解
- You mean they wanna fuck Jim.  - Exactly.
正解
Exactly.
而我
Well, me,
我只上过Jean
I've only fucked Jean.
*两岸*
*All along the banks*
什么
What?
哦是啊
Oh, yeah.
哦 对啊 你懂的
Oh, yeah. You know.
如果想在"煤气灯"表演的话...
If you wanna play the Gaslight...
谢了 女士们先生们 谢谢
Thanks. Ladies and gentlemen, thanks.
- 谢谢  - 谢谢你 Pappi Corsicato
- Thanks.  - Thank you, Pappi Corsicato.
让我们有请Elizabeth Hobby
Please give a great big welcome to Elizabeth Hobby
来自阿肯色州的诶尔诺拉
from Elinora in Arkansas.
谢谢 谢谢你们 女士们先生们
Thank you. Thank you, ladies and gentlemen.
谢谢你们 你们太好了
Thank you. You're so nice.
这是我在纽约的首场演出
This is my first show in New York.
你是怎么得到表演机会的 Betty
How'd you get the gig, Betty?
呃 我准备唱这首歌
Um, I'm gonna do this song.
和很多我表演过的歌一样
It's like a lot of the songs I do.
这首歌伴着我长大
It's one I grew up with.
哈哈 拜托Llewyn 给我留点信誉
Ha, ha. Come on, Llewyn. Give me a little credit.
*我要离开了 离开最亲爱的你*
*I'm a-goin' away To leave you, love*
*我要去很远的地方 漂洋过海*
*I'm going far over the sea*
*但终有一日 我会回到你身边*
*But I'll return to you someday*
*所以我要走一万里*
*So I go 10,000 miles*
- 你的干草卷呢  - 嘘
- Where's your hay bale?  - Shh!
*起风暴了*
*The storms are on*
哈 你的玉米烟斗呢(廉价烟)
Huh? Where's your corncob pipe?
*大海啊*
*The ocean*
你穿的是方格内裤吗
Are you wearing gingham panties?
嘘
Shh!
哈
Huh?
- 操你妈 欠操的骗子 - 来啊 给我们展示一下你的内裤
- Fuck you, you fucking phony.  - Come on, show us your panties.
- 闭嘴  - 给我们展示你的内裤 Betty
- Shut up.  - Show us your panties, Betty.
- 够了  - 好了
- That's enough. - Fine.
操老天 我恨死他妈的民谣了
Oh, God, I hate fucking folk music.
- 好了 Eddie 叫Florio  - 他妈的我恨死民谣了
- Okay, Eddie. We might need Florio.  - I fucking hate folk music.
滚你妈的Florio 滚你妈的 Pappi
Fuck Florio. Fuck you, Pappi.
这表演就是狗屎
The show is bullshit.
四个爱尔兰佬和一个老妈子
Four micks and Grandma Moses.
Llewyn 快进来
Llewyn. Come on in.
Lillian正在做她最拿手的塔博勒色拉(黎巴嫩生菜)
Lillian's making her famous tabbouleh salad.
哦 Mitch 我实在是太感谢了
Oh, Mitch, I really appreciate this.
特别是上次之后 我不知道有多抱歉
After last time, I just can't tell you how sorry I am.
别提了
Oh, forget it.
说起Mike我们都有点儿敏感
We all get a little emotional over Mike.
只是表达的方式不同
It comes out in different ways.
他那么有活力 你知道的 那么有才华
He had such life, you know? Such a talent.
失去他像是在心上挖个大洞 一个大洞
It's a big hole. A big hole.
你要在我们这里呆多久
How long will you be with us?
一两天就好 如果可以的话
Just a day or two, if that's okay.
- 等到我能解决掉下个...  - 没问题 好的
- Just until I can figure out the next... - Sure, yeah.
你认识Arlen和Dodi Gamble吗
Do you know Arlen and Dodi Gamble?
这位是Llewyn Davis 我们的朋友 民谣歌手
This is Llewyn Davis, our folk-singer friend.
你是Jim和Jean的好友
You're Jim and Jean's friend.
嗯 算是吧
Uh, sort of.
Jim给我们表演过那张唱片里一首"拜托 肯尼迪先生"
Jim played us a pressing of that record, "Please, Mr. Kennedy."
- 那首歌特别有趣  - 非常
- It was hysterical.  - So funny.
肯定会大红的 伙计
That's gonna be a hit, man.
拿版税了吗 喔哦 宝贝儿
Royalties on that? Whoa, Nelly.
真希望我也干你们这一行 我是说 一首歌大卖就能解决所有问题
I wish I was in your business. I mean, one hit could fix you up.
- 呃 是啊  - Llewyn
- Uh, yeah... - Llewyn.
- Lillian...  - 抱歉我上次让你难过了
- Lillian...  - I am so sorry I upset you.
不不不不 你是在向我道歉吗
No, no, no. You're apologizing to me?
- 是的  - 不用
- Yeah.  - No.
我去
Holy shit.
- 哦嘿  - 哦
- On! Heh.  - Oh.
哦 真好 挺好的 你们又养了一只猫
Oh, that's... That's good. You got a new cat.
- 不是  - 不是 他回家了
- No.  - No, he came home.
他自己找到了回家的路
Found his way back.
门卫昨天早上听到有什么东西在挠门
The doorman heard something scratching yesterday morning.
- 特别早 凌晨的时候  - 是啊 看
- Early morning, the wee hours. - Yeah, see?
它是Ulysses
It's Ulysses.
- 它叫...Ulysses  - Ulysses
- It's... Ulysses?  - Ulysses.
那是他的名字
That's its name?
有人吗
Hello?
*我将不久于人世*
*And I'll be dead and gone*
*我不介意被绞死*
*I wouldn't mind the hanging*
*只是可怜见的 我不想永远困在一方坟墓*
*But the laying in the grave's so long Poor boy*
*我也曾游走四方*
*I've been all around this world*
你们之前可能听过这首
You probably heard that one before.
如果一首歌从来不曾新过 也永远不会过时
If it was never new, and it never gets old,
估计就是民谣了
then it's a folk song.
好了 我走之前最后一首
All right, one more before I go.
*如果我有双翅*
*If I had wings*
*像诺亚身旁的白鸽*
*Like Norah's dove*
*我将飞越河流*
*I'd fly up the river*
*飞向我的所爱*
*To the one I love*
*别了*
*Fare thee well*
*哦 我的爱人*
*Oh, honey*
*别了*
*Fare thee well*
*在一个清晨*
*Early one morning*
*细雨飘零*
*Drizzling rain*
*在我心里*
*And in my heart*
*感到疼痛难忍*
*I felt an achin' pain*
*别了*
*Fare thee well*
*哦 我的爱人*
Oh, honey
*别了*
*Fare thee well*
*某一个清晨*
*One of these mornings*
*不会太久*
*It won't be long*
*你会呼唤我的名字*
*You'll call my name*
*但我已经离开*
*And I'll be gone*
*别了*
*Fare thee well*
*我的爱人*
*Oh, honey*
*别了 别了*
*Fare, fare thee well*
*如果我有双翅*
*If I had wings*
*像诺亚鸽子一样*
*Like Norah's dove*
*我将飞越河流*
*I'd fly up the river*
*飞向我的所爱*
*To the one I love*
*哦 别了*
*Oh, fare thee well*
*哦 我的爱人*
*Oh, honey*
*别了*
*Fare thee well*
以上
That's what I got.
- 你和Mikey一起唱过这首歌  - 是的
- You and Mikey used to do that song.  - Yeah.
孩子 你昨天晚上有点混乱
Boy, you were some mess last night.
是 对不起 Pappi 我是个傻逼
Yeah, sorry, Pappi. I'm an asshole.
我才管不着呢
I don't give a shit.
- 你一个朋友在后巷  - 我的朋友
- Your friend is out back.  - My friend?
他说是你的朋友 一个西装男
Said he was a friend of yours. Guy in a suit.
*哦 我要向你告别 我的真爱*
*Oh, it's fare thee well My darling true*
*天亮那一刻我就要离开*
*I'm leaving in the first hour Of the morn*
你这货挺有趣 哈
You a funny boy, huh?
什么
What?
管不住你的大嘴是吧
Had to open your big mouth.
我只是为了糊口
That's what I do for a living.
糊口 通过取笑民谣吗
What you do. Make fun of folks up there?
你昨天在观众席上大放厥词
You sit there in the audience last night, yelling your crap.
那是演出啊 伙计 怎么可能不张嘴
You yell stuff, man. It's a show.
那不是你的表演
It wasn't your show.
又不是歌剧 混球 只是他妈的酒吧演出
It's not the opera, jackass. It's a fucking basket hou...
我们马上就要离开这臭粪坑了 你在里面享受吧
We're leaving this fucking cesspool. You can have it.
糊口
What you do.
- 我太太想在上面唱首歌  - 嗷
- My wife up there trying to sing. - Unh.
电波字幕组 诚心诚译
官方网站:dbfansub.com
新浪微博:@电波字幕组
欢迎加入我们